[Music]
hello everyone my name is guy royce i'm
a developer advocate at redis and uh
welcome to my workshop this is the express and
redis workshop express and redisome express and
write a stack i don't know that i have a really
good title for it but we're going to call it a
using redis with express workshop thingy uh
and well today i'm going to show you how to
build a simple node.js api with express and redis
stack we're going to use redisome to do that uh
to interact with reta stack and uh i'm gonna do
this mostly with a bunch of code so uh expect a
lot of vs code action i don't really have any
pictures or anything other than well this one
i am going into this uh assuming that you know
a bit of express so uh although uh i'm not using
express in a particularly sophisticated way um
basic knowledge should serve you just fine and
to be honest if you don't haven't touched
express at all you don't know much about it
you don't know anything about it you're probably
going to be fine it's it's not anything it's i'm
not it's just rocket surgery so um i'm also
assuming that you've got redistac installed
i've watched an earlier video or read a
blog or something telling you how to do it
it's possible that content you've
consumed will even be created by future me
uh i guess i'll find out so i'm assuming you
got uh read us up and running with read a stack
and that you've got some basic express knowledge
not a lot and i'm assuming also that you don't
know a gosh darned thing about reticem and
well that's good because that's the point
of the workshop i'm going to show you how to
use express plus retisom to build a simple api
and that api is going to be a little person api
where we're going to do like you know hey go get
their name search for them by name and their age
and you know those sorts of things they may be
their location so um so we should start out with
some what the hecks are right so what the heck
is redisome uh you may not have heard of reticem
well retisom is a a library that uh well actually
was written by yours truly that provides uh
object mapping for redis which is to say it maps
redis data types specifically hashes or json
documents in this workshop we're going to use json
to javascript classes and objects uh and it allows
you to search over those hashes and json documents
um to do that it uses redis json and write a
search what are redis json what are the search
well for starters they're included in reda stack
but redis json and redis search are modules uh
modules are like plugins they extend the
capabilities of redis so if you've got a you
know a module like json it adds new data types uh
json documents and adds new commands uh commands
that manipulate json documents to redis and read a
search does the same thing but it adds commands to
create indexes or indices and to then do search so
that's redis home that's a little bit about what
redis json and reddit search are uh and
even what modules are uh we're gonna use
all these capabilities uh to build a relatively
restful uh person api relatively restful you know
it'll do all the crud operations and a little
bit a few other things they'll have basic data
like the age of that person their name uh and
we're gonna even throw in locations so we can
do like a simple location tracking app so maybe
you uh are using an app and it's like well this
person checked in at this restaurant and then
they checked in at this you know gas station
or whatever you can totally follow along with us
that's the intention of what we're building here
is that we're building something that that
we i i'm building this thing here for you
to follow along so the idea is you can watch
the code that i'm showing you pause the video
um type it in try it out see it work and then
resume the video and then do the next step um and
so there's a repo that you're going to use the
starter code to get this doing it's got a bare
bones express application with swagger
uh and it's got um three branches in it
uh one branch is the solution branch uh that's
the cheater code that's the code that you can
look at you say hey how does this thing work
you just go look at your solution branch
there are a steps branch which i'm
going to walk through all the steps
i'm not typing this whole time i'm going to use
a little tool to walk through my individual git
commits and you can go see the process that i
follow by following those steps too and there's
the main branch which is the one that you'll
clone that will actually just be your starter code
and uh the link to that github repo it'll be
in the description somewhere below hopefully or
wherever you found this video so that's what we're
building that's sort of the stuff you need to do
so go clone that repo and uh pause the video and
then come back and then i'll explain to you what
we're building in greater detail well welcome
back here on my screen we've got um persons
we want to store person data in uh redis using
redisone and i've got a small collection of json
files here in this person's folder and the repo
that uh you should have a clone of uh so i've got
like chris stapleton they're all musicians uh so
this is well that's chris stapleton joan jett uh
you could tell i'm a gen xer um and we got uh
carrie uh livgren who is the person from kansas
that did all we are as dust in the wind that was
his song so i've got uh various artists here so
let's look at uh let's look at chris staple now
let's look at jojet so uh the data we have that
we want to store is a basic json document
here this will be the request body when we
do the uh posts to create these so first name and
last name as strings we got an age uh joan jett is
shockingly 63 years old now um a verified flag the
idea here is are they verified on you know do they
have the little blue check mark next to them or
not uh their location you know this would be the
location tracking aspect are they you know what's
their longitude and latitude right this minute
and we have a little date here that represents
when that was last updated with a little iso
8609 date format we've got some skills that that
person has i picked some random ones that seem
appropriate for their uh their uh their aptitudes
and so joan has singing guitar because she plays
the guitar and uh she has black eyeliner because
she always used a lot of black eyeliner and her
personal statement is of course i love rock and
roll so put another dime in the jukebox baby
so this is the kind of data we're going to be
adding pretty pretty pretty straightforward right
so now that we know what we're building and what
the data looks like let's let's actually do all
the prereqs let's get everything set up so uh
the first thing that the first thing that we need
to make sure of is that you've got red of stack
up and running so you've got some redis version
running you you might be running that uh local
machine you might be running that in the cloud
you might have the password you might not
but let's make sure it's up and running
i've got redis up and running on my machine so
i'm gonna go to redis insight and confirm that
my redis instance is up and running so here we
are in redis insight here's a bunch of databases
i've got mine configured already if you want
to add one you just click add a redis database
uh i've got one called that local one which
is just localhost 6379 with uh no password
and uh this has two things here we've got a little
keys here i've got some old data from my previous
uh rehearsals of this talk uh and i'm going to uh
prove that redis is up and running uh i guess i
can just refresh it and yeah they're still working
uh by deleting everything so nukem from orbit
it's the only way to be sure so i'm gonna run the
flush all command this is a very dangerous command
it literally just deletes everything without
asking never ever ever ever run this casually
in production and but now it's all gone so if i go
back to my key list here and hit refresh it's all
gone you can see that stream's not there anymore
and so i have wiped the database and confirmed
that redis does indeed exist and is configured
and running and everything on my machine cool
the starter code that i've got here uh
this this library here there's not much
there there's a server.js and a little else
let me close some of these other windows here
but it needs some basic configuration uh if
you look here in the server.js i'm using uh
env and so what that does is it looks for a
file with the name of emv in your root and then
pulls environment variables out of it and so i've
got a sample.env in the repo that you can clone
that you just cloned and so you just need to copy
this file to env and the only configuration it
has it is the redis url and so here mine
is red is cool and slash localhost 6379
if you've got red a stack running locally this
is probably what yours is as well uh and all
i've done is i've copied that to env and deleted
some comments and so this is really the only part
that matters this is not a complicated file
so um set this to whatever your redis url is
it's probably what i have but it might not
be to be depending on how you've set redis up
so once you've got that established there's one
last thing that's kind of important and uh for
me it's already set up if you look here i got an
nvmrc i like to use node version manager and this
is the version of node i'm using so here we've got
16.3 which is the version i have you can use an
earlier one but there is a limit so um if i if you
do if i go no dash version you see i'm using node
16.3 but i'm in this example i'm using top level
awaits so used to be when you have an await in
your javascript code you'd have to wrap it in some
function that was async starting with node 14.6
you can do top level awaits so you can wait well
without having to be inside of the function at the
top level and so i'm using that in all my samples
so you need to make sure you're using node 14.8
or more recent or more recent version so i'm using
16.3 should work just fine with 14.8 or higher so
if you don't have that pause the video go get it
right now so that's the setup uh let's take a look
at uh what sort of skeleton code what's the
starter code look like and and what it looks like
is a well a bog standard express app so here we've
got uh you know i mentioned this earlier we're
importing that dot m for your uh configuration
with our redis url i'm bringing in express of
course because this is an express app i've got
swagger in here so we gotta you may have seen that
as i sliding back and forth here i've got swagger
so that you don't have to mess around with like
postman or doing curl or anything like that you
just get a nice little ui it defines the uh the
interface uh the api we're creating and lets you
test it as well so i'm using swagger ui to do that
and i'm using yaml js to convert my yaml files
to json so that swagger ui can deal with them
and then i create a brand new express app and
tell it to use json so hey if you get handed an
object as a result assume this json and convert
it to json and give it the right content type and
everything uh here's where i set up the swagger
in the root of this api so we've got comp swagger
document equals yaml.load this loads the yaml file
here which has the api specified in it so if we
look at this file we can see that hey look there's
yaml you're welcome to look at that on your own
time um so we load that yaml file in and then
this yaml js turns that into a javascript object
and then we uh call app.use and say on the
root use swagger ui and i mean honestly i
don't know exactly how this thing works i just
copied it from their documentation on github
so and i know that it does work so that's that's
the key thing here um so we're we're binding our
swagger ui to the root level and then we tell
our app to listen up for 8080. and that's it
now i should be able to just run this so let's go
ahead and clear this noise up and say npm start
and i'm using uh no daemon or nodemon
depending on how you want to say it and
so as i make changes it should just
restart automatically so let's uh
let's refresh this here just to
show that it's localhost 8080.
um command shift r and it reloads so uh this is
the swagger uri showing all the things that i
find in that api dot yaml we've got our person
put get post and delete these are our crud
operations for the user create read update delete
uh and we've got some search options and we have
a location updater thingy that we'll explain
later so we've got our server up and running
uh it's over here and we can we can invoke it like
if i hit execute here and we can see that we uh
get an uh get a html page back because this route
hasn't been implemented this is probably expressed
saying hey you can't do that route thing so
swagger is working yeah working [Laughter]
and that's pretty much the starter code so um
let's start making this more than starter code
so i am going to uh bring in the first few bits
here uh we need to create a client we need to
connect to redis and retisom does that using
a client and so let me bring that code up here
and so here we have a client.js file that i've
just created we import client from redis home
we get our url from the environment now this
is from that emv file uh that this ultimately
comes from and then all we do is we create a
new client with a new client and then we call
open on it immediately and open returns itself
it's a builder pattern and so then we can kind
of one line this and say wait new client open
and then the url and then we have a client and
then all we have to do is export that client easy
peasy we have connected to redis with retizone
i like to put my client in this file by itself
that way if i have multiple repositories which
we're going to get to in a minute we can sort of
guarantee that we have one and only one client
which works great with uh node
because node is single threaded
and redis is single threaded and so having a
single connection works out really well because
there's never going to be two processes using that
connection simultaneously so works out great so
let's uh continue on with this so now that we
have a client uh we need to create uh and we have
a client that redisohm can use to talk to redis
we need to create uh our entity and our schema
so redisome needs an entity which is uh the things
that we're reading and writing this is the person
and a schema schema is the thing that defines how
redis talks to uh how redis maps that entity to
json or hashes in our case json and what the
field names are and if they're they're aliased
and and all the types and those sorts of things so
it's it's that data about how to take the entity
and send it through us and how to take the
thing in redis and move it to the entity
to define an entity well that's it all right just
one line one line of code here and we define a
class within the entity name that we want so we
i've picked person because they're persons and
it needs to extend the entity class that we've
imported here and then it's just an empty class
when we define our schema redis ohm will add a
whole bunch of properties to the entity for you
and you can actually enter your own uh properties
in here as well so if you wanted to add say a
special property that like maybe reads a couple
of the other properties and computes some new
property you could do that we're not going to do
that for this example though once we've got that
person we need to say how do we map this entity
to uh redis and we do that by creating a schema so
here i've got a constant person schema i call new
schema and i pass in the class that i just defined
this very boring class up here and then we pass
in this big object down here and this is just a
javascript object that has uh keys and values for
all of uh it has all that metadata i was talking
about earlier so we have a field in uh redis and
that we're going to add to our entity called first
name it is a string so in redis home a string is
a whole string we're matching the entire string
or or not there's no partial string matching so
we'll say you know find all the the people with
the name chris or like uh chris stapleton or joan
for joan chat the last name is also a string same
idea hey you know so we got first name and last
name they're both strings so we can look for
all the people named stapleton with the last name
but we couldn't look for people whose name starts
with the staple it has to be the whole string we
get age that's a number so uh joan jets amazing
63 years uh we've got verified that's a boolean
and so these boolean fields and these uh number
fields and these string fields will be stored
as javascript strings and numbers and booleans
and in radis they will be stored under red and
redis json as a string in a json document and as a
number in a json document and as a boolean
in a json document so it's true to type
we've got a location here which is a point a
point is a point on the globe a geo location
so it's a latitude and longitude and so this is
stored as a latitude and longitude in redis redis
stores that internally as a string with
the longitude comma the latitude uh and
redisome maps that to a simple javascript object
that's got a longitudinal latitude property
location updated is a date this is a javascript
date write us turns treats that as a javascript
date that we know and love and hate uh in
redis it's stored as a unix epoch time in
the number of uh seconds since the beginning
of uh since the beginning of the unix epoch
uh we've got a stringer right here so the skills
is a string array this is skills that that person
might have and like in joan jett's case she had
a singing guitar and black eyeliner um that is
a string array and that is actually stored
in redis uh json as a an array um of strings
and and it's actually stored as an array in
javascript as well and uh they all have a personal
statement and that's a type text and so text is
kind of like string in the sense that if you let's
if you pull it back it's just stored
in a javascript into javascript string
but the the text statement or the text field type
is uh different when it comes to searching it
uh when we search for like the first name
or last name it's all or nothing match the
whole whole name or don't match it or match the
state or don't match it the personal statement is
full text search smart it knows how to search
text that's human readable so like paragraphs
and essays and statements so you know joan
jetts personal statements i love rock and roll
and the text search is smart um it can
match on uh grammatically equivalent things
so if you were searching for the word uh give
it might it would also match gives given giving
and gave because it knows that those are all
grammatically equivalent as far as search is
concerned it also ignores common words like a n or
the because they're not useful to search on and so
uh it's very powerful it's very useful but um
it doesn't it's not suitable for doing whole
searches and you can't say well give me like
these first 10 you know give me a string that
starts with like these 10 words exactly
with the stop words and everything that's
harder to do with read a search so you can
match on whole words with search up here
or you can match full text between the two of
those you can handle almost any search criteria
you'd want and then you add in the numbers and
the strings and the dates and it's it's fantastic
so that's what we got so far that was
a lot on a little bit of code wasn't it
um once you have a schema
that's defining this mapping
on all these field types then you can use the
client remember the client to fetch a repository
the repository is the thing that allows us to do
all the operations with the entities it creates
the entities it reads the entities it updates
the entities it deletes the entities it searches
for entities it does all the stuff that we want
to do with entities and so we say client.fetch
repository pass in that schema and we get a
repository which we're going to of course export
now we have everything we need to do to talk
to redis using reticent uh so let's go to the
other side of things let's go to the front
end let's go and define a router for express
that'll show us how to do that that'll let us
actually create read update and delete things so
i have created in here a router person router
and so i'm doing basic express stuff import
the router from express import the personal
repository that we just created from the
person.js and create a router that we export
and we're going to create some
stubbed out routes here we got the
the create the read the update and delete the put
to get the post and the delete put doesn't take
an id of course because we'll generate that
for you uh get post and delete do take ids
and then we need to bind this in our server.js so
if we go to server.js here we've got here we've
added a line app.use and we added the slash person
route is going to be handled by person router
so you go to slice person slash id and you
do a delete that will delete that person
there's our personal writer so
let's flush one of these out and
see what it looks like so i always like to start
with create because you have to have a create you
have to have a thing before you can read it update
it or delete it so gotta have a thing first so
i'm gonna do create here so we do a router.put
slash this would be slash person slash we have
a convenient little method on the repository
called create and save create and save takes a
simple javascript object containing all the person
data in the format that redis ohm is expecting it
through wonderful coincidence we happen to have
uh objects that are in exactly that format so um
so yeah so all we have to do is call create and
save and just pass in the body from our request
and then that will save it and return
a person with an id added to it
so this person will have all the things
it has and it will have an entity id on it
and then we just return that person on
the response so this should be working
let's try it who should we add let's add uh do
you want to add joan jett or chris stapleton
let's do chris stapleton so i'm going to select
all of chris stapleton and we're going to go over
here to our swagger interface we're not going to
do persons all we're going to do a create person
and create person uh takes a the body there
i have a sample body with rupert holmes
he's the guy who created the pina colada
song but we're gonna we're gonna add
fish stapleton and we can see here we've got all
those fields that we were talking about before
and let's go ahead and execute that and we get
a response back here here's our curl put our url
and then here's our data this url we used and
then here's the response we get back we get the
entity id this is the unique id representing that
record uh it's a eulid which is uh like a uuid
but um tidier that might be a good way to describe
it uh it's more compact uh and um so it's because
it's not using hexadecimal encoding it's using i
think it's called base 32 encoding uh where it has
fewer letters and it's very url friendly so we use
eulids and then all of the data that we just added
and so this should exist in redis now we did
you know we went through our code here if we
go back to our code the person router uh
called personal repository create and save
let's see if it actually created
it we'll go out into redis insight
we'll refresh our keys and we see oh look hey
there's a key it's a json document um it's got
the key name is person colon and a ulid this
is the ulid we just uh copied um this person
colon the person comes from the the entity name
so our class our entity class is called person
so we just interrogate that and that becomes the
key is the entity name plus the uh the uh the ulid
so if we click on this we can look and see that
there is chris stapleton he has 43 he's verified
this is his location which is lexington kentucky
the location updated there it is is the unix epoch
time uh we can expand his skills here and see
that he has singing football and coal mining
which i'm sure he learned from
his parents her father probably
um and it is uh his personal statement is
a line from that song sometimes i cry so um
i'm not going to read it because it's too sad um
so yeah it created it huzzah okay well let's uh
let's read it now we've created let's read so let
me go to the next little bit of code here let's
flush out our our read or our get and so this is
going to be slash person slash id where it's that
ulid and uh we have the id passed in so it's just
two lines of code we use that person repository
we call fetch and we pass in the id and that
returns a person and then we return the person
let's see if that works so we did a create up here
let's do a get we're going to try it out we'll
post in post and paste in that id call execute
and we can see that there indeed is chris
stapleton and all that data we had before
and it's converted that uh the the unix timestamp
to a nice iso 8601 date uh the location if we if
we go back here and look at the location you'll
see its uh longitude comma latitude as a string
and we've converted that into nice little objects
here in redison so reticom does all that for you
cool and we could probably
let's try this here we should be able to just go
ahead and get this url here so this is just a get
so uh we can easily we don't need to use swagger
to do the get so that gets us that data as well
okay so create read what's next update
so update's a little more verbose but it's not
particularly complicated this is an all or nothing
update so you're taking um the uh the entire
request body and you're replacing every field
we're not updating individual fields here so you
pass in an id you pass in that request body uh you
fetch based on the id and then you uh that person
that you fetch you you replace all the properties
with uh the first name the last name
the the age the verified the location
all the properties that are in that body and here
i'm doing a knowledge coalescing operator here
so if first name is undefined then it sets it to
null if last name is undefined it sets it to null
and once we've done that then we call save
passing in that person and then it'll update it
and then we send that person back so let's
uh let's update uh young master stapleton
let's copy his data here
and we'll collapse that and go to
post to update and we'll try it out
and that's uh his data and i know
the id is different i don't want to
get that id there too i don't i don't
want to create a new record by mistake so
so we're going to call person id that's the id
and we're going to update that and we're going to
make chris stapleton uh we're going to make him
18. he said he's young again he'll be so happy
and uh here we see chris stapleton age 18. and if
we go back to here and refresh we see that chris
stapleton is age 18. so we've done an update we've
done a create we've done an update we've done a
delete we're going to create a read and update now
we're going to do a delete so delete is also very
short you simply call remove and pass in the
id and then here i'm returning the id back so
let's go ahead and delete this wonderful
chris stapleton who is now 18 years old
and execute it okay so it
issues a delete against that url
if we go back to here and refresh
error key with this name does not exist
that's correct it does not we refresh this
we'll see that uh chris stapleton is now gone
so create read update and delete using redisome
and express pretty cool but wait there's more
i wouldn't i wouldn't leave you with just
that uh because there's more that we can
do there's more neat stuff so let's we
got a whole bunch of searching to do so
we want to not just have to find these musicians
by their these persons by their id we would want
to look for persons that match certain criteria
we might have a lot more than you know we might
have a lot of persons in there and maybe you want
to find people that are of a certain age or with a
particular last name or they have particular words
in their personal statement or or are verified um
you can totally do that with retisome
that's what the redis search part of it is
so uh the first thing you have to do in
order to use search is you have to create
an index so here in the person repository in the
person.js i've added this line of code right here
uh grade index what this will do is it will create
an index and store it in redis and that index will
then allow us to use search commands and if i go
out and refresh it actually creates an index and
it creates a hash of that index out there
so we've got a little string it's got a
hash in there there's a little signature that
represents that index if you change your schema
it will compare these and this is all it's just
plumbing for redis i read a zone but it'll compare
these and if they're different it will rebuild
it'll delete and rebuild the index so you can just
call create index and not worry about it uh but uh
behind the scenes if you say well let's make age
you know another type or you know change your
data in some way uh it will uh rebuild that
index accordingly so we we got our uh we call call
create index that's the first thing you have to
do this is a really easy thing to miss and forget
when you're doing this you're like i got my schema
and everything and you forget to call create index
and then you're like why aren't all my searches
working it's because you didn't call create index
i've done it myself and i wrote the library so
i'm going to create another router for all of
the searching we want to do and so this is just
sort of bog standard router templating stuff so
let's see what's next i'm going to add the easiest
of all searches which is give me everything
star so here's the stubbed out route for that
if you go to slash persons slash routes or
persons slash person slash all this will code
will get implemented the implementation
for this is actually pretty simple
we use the personal repository where before we
call create or save or remove or fetch here we
call search and then search returns an object of
its own which you can call return on and all which
will return all of them there's other options you
can return like paginations you can just get the
count if you want there's a lot of options here
we're just going to call return all for now and
you can explore the other ways of returning
data and the other other ways of doing this
later in your in your when we're done but so
this is just going to search and return all
this is just searching on star and then it's
going to get an array of persons back and then
it's just going to send that back and it'll turn
into a json object and we got one last little bit
here we need to do because i haven't bound this
route this all route to anything in server.js
so in here i'm going to bind slash persons to
the search router so and with that we should
be able to uh search all so let's go and get
all the persons execute and well it worked
it's not very exciting but it worked uh we
don't have any data so there's nothing to
return so let's get some data in there i have
in my repository here a a little shell script
called low data load data.sh all it does is go
through this directory and take all the json files
and load them up and that's that that's all
it does so um let's run that really quick
uh i'll go ahead and stop the server change your
persons dot slash load and if you're using windows
um sorry but uh you should be able to create
a batch file that does something similar so
oh i [Laughter] see this happens to the best
of us right i actually need the server running
in order to connect to it so
let's let's create a new tab
and then uh go back here and then npm
starts get our server running and then
in this new tab we'll do we'll do the
uh the um while we're in it already
it will run the script okay so now it's created
a bunch of musicians to populate our data here
and if we go out to redis here we can see that
we've got the whole mess of persons there's joan
jett there's justin timberlake uh this is the guy
who wrote the toto's africa song i got eminem all
kinds of all kinds of folks and uh just for fun
let's go ahead and find chris stapleton in here
always the last place you look
right let's make chris stapleton 18.
because you know i like chris
stapleton he deserves it
okay and i actually did that for a reason
you'll find you'll find out soon enough
so now if i do a person's all search hit execute i
get all the person so there's joan jett and carrie
and rupert and david justin and
ivan and marshall and chris cool
so uh returning everything is all fine and
dandy but uh obviously we want to do things
that are a little more sophisticated than that
so uh let's go ahead and search by last name
so i've added another route here uh router.get by
last name and then you just specify the last name
uh this is um not terribly complicated
uh we we go ahead and pull that last
name out and assign it to a variable just
to make our code a little bit tidy here
and then instead of calling search return
all we say search and then we say where
and then where takes a string and that string
is the field name that we defined in our schema
so way back here in person.js we've got
a first name and a last name and an age
we're using last name so we want
to use this value right here
so that's what gets passed in here and then
we're saying equals and then we provide whatever
string we want to provide in there here we're
passing in last name and then call return all
and this will create a search that finds all
of the users that have a particular last name
this equals here is semantic sugar
you can say is equal is equal to
right um you know there's there's lots of
variations on this we're just
going to go with uh equals
uh but you can say is equal to or is
equals or does not does equal or you've
got lots of options there's lots of you
see does equal it all does the same thing
and when you go you go to retisom's
documentation there's examples of
all these there for you to play with so
we've got this little bit of code here
we can search by last name let's go ahead
and search by last name so let's look for
uh we'll look for holmes we'll look
over rupert holmes the pina colada song
person because i like pina
coladas and walks in the rain
so here we've searched by last name of holmes you
can see our url is uh persons by last name holmes
and here is the rupert's data so there's
his entity id and he's 75 years old
as of the time i created this data verified on
uh whatever this app is that we're building uh
this is his location which i think is somewhere in
the uk and um yeah all the data and he likes pina
coladas and taking blocks in the right so we were
able to search by last name we could search by uh
stapleton instead and then we get chris stapleton
there we go chris stapleton who is not 18.
cool uh in addition searching by strings we can
search by numbers so i've added a line here that
finds everyone that's 21 or older aka old enough
to drink in america so if you go to person slash
old enough to drink in america it will return
everyone except for chris stapleton so let's
let's try that one out um this one doesn't have
any arguments you just run it hit execute and
we'll see that there's joan jett and carrie and
rupert and david and justin timberlake and ivan
and eminem but no chris stapleton because
he is not old enough to drink in america
cool we can also do booleans and again if we
look at these queries here this is gte for
greater than or equal to we it also you can also
type in greater than or equal to or is greater
than or equal to there's a bunch of semantic
sugar uh to let you do this however you want
um for booleans very similar situation uh we want
to do a git for non-verified users not verified
and not unverified but non-verified so where
verified is not true and so here we're saying
where verified that's that field name is
is just a little binder word it doesn't do
anything it just makes it read like a sentence not
inverts the query and true says is equal to true
so where verified is not true now you might
be wondering why would we want to search for
a not true why don't we just search for
false well if the true field was missing
or the verified field was missing then it would
be null which would be neither true nor false
but we want things that are not true so not true
would return false or null so this catches both
of those uh so but we're saying we're verified we
could actually say verified not true and return
all and this will give us all the non-verified
users and we can go out and test that very quickly
and see that we do indeed get
false false false and false
and of course you can use all of these together uh
you you are restricted to searching by one field
so here i've got verified drinkers with last name
last name so these are people who are over the
age of 21 that are verified and have a last name
that equals the last name that you passed in so
all we're doing is saying search where verified
is true and ages 21 and last name and this could
be and there's also or so you can do or as well if
you like um and you can create more complex ones
those are documented on the website for
redisome there'll be links to that later
so go check those out too um but yeah that will
do a verified drinkers with last name so let's
hit that url really quick just to show that
that works verified drinkers with last name
i'm going to try it out we're going to find uh
verified drinkers with the last name of timberlake
and so that finds justin timberlake who
is verified is over 21 and does have the
last name of timberlake so that works as well uh
next we're going to show off um full text search
so that's this little bit here we're going to
do a full text search against their statements
so here we have with statement containing and then
text and so here we can pass in word or words uh
that we want to search for in a full text way um
this means the ways i described earlier when i
was describing the text field uh the uh you know
it understands the grammar it understands common
words that aren't useful in a search and makes
appropriate checks and so if we search for like
the word walk it will match walks if we search
for the word uh give it'll match uh given and gave
um and it ignores words like a n and the
so um to do that we just uh use the matches
verb here so we say where personal statement
matches and then we give it some text to match
don't you cannot use equals on these that won't
work you can't check a text field for equality
you can only search for words within that text
field if you want to do quality use a string
so here we're saying where the the personal
statement matches text that we pass in and then
we return all of those and this is actually kind
of neat the way it works so i'm going to look for
walk walk is a good example because i'm going
to search for walk and then our result finds
rupert holmes and chris stapleton uh so rupert
holmes says i like pina coladas and taking walks
plural even though we searched for
walk so it matched it anyhow right
and um here uh chris stapleton used the word walk
in his personal statement if i add rain do it
now we're just going to get
rupert because he has walk
and rain act let's do a take
as well that should work
yeah so taking got map to take so you can see
that stemming happening there where it understands
the grammar of english and it does support other
languages um and the other thing is is it ignores
common words like it's got the rain and so if
you start with that it'll match but it doesn't
have the word a in it or an so let's search
for let's add an and a and run it you can see
it still matches even though those words aren't
found in the personal statement so it's it knows
that a and and uh and things like that are common
words that aren't really useful for search because
it just matches everything and so it pulls
those out and so this is the full text search of
redis search being being utilized here very easily
from uh some redisome code so that's pretty neat
let's uh let's look at the next search one and
this is kind of my favorite uh just because
geo searching is kind of cool so we can do geo
fields we can look at points on the globe and
then say search for things within a radius of that
point so uh our route here is to get persons near
a point on the globe and a radius of that from
that point in miles i i chose to use miles because
uh i like freedom units because i use miles
because i'm an american sorry sorry not sorry
uh and so uh we're just going to pull out
the longitude the latitude and the radius
from our url here right and we're going to
convert those to numbers obviously this will
this could fail if you passed in invalid data
here i'm you know this you can make express
better this is just kind of show you how these
things fit together um and then when we do a
person's repository.search like we've done for all
of these we can say where location that'd be that
latitude and longitude that longitude and latitude
so we say in radius here we give it a circle
that we build up and we can say circle
that longitude latitude radius and
and these are all the numbers that we passed
in and then we say we want to use miles
uh this could be miles this could be kilometers
this could be uh feet this could be meters i use
miles and then we return all so uh what this will
do is we pick a point in the globe and then say
find everyone within 20 miles of this point which
is kind of cool so let's uh let's test that out
so we got uh try it out we're going to look for
every people that are at um let's let's just do
0.0 zero and those just do really long distances
so we'll start with null island which is
off the coast of africa here which is not a
real place uh so latitude longitude zero zero
there's a buoy there and that's about
it and if we search for like a 20 mile
radius we're not going to find anyone because
there's nothing within 20 miles of that so
see we've got an empty response there so
let's go with like a 2 000 mile radius
still haven't found anyone because it's pretty
far from things let's go with a 5 000 mile radius
okay so we found rupert holmes that's who i
figured we'd find uh because he's in the uk
and so we uh he he's in that location if
we widen even further we could probably get
someone in the united states here
uh oh dropped it to a thousand we got
ten thousand so that yeah so now we're
getting some americans here this is jon
ja and it's probably just about everyone
so um so yeah so that's how you can do a geo
search where say hey i'm at a point i want to find
the people around me um that could be useful if
you're at a location and you're using this app and
you want to find your buddies right it's like oh
who's who's around me who's within you know half
a mile of me or you know 500 feet or whatever so
that's pretty much uh search but um i want to add
just a little bit more to the app because i think
it'd be kind of cool i want to add this sort of
location tracking ability so what that means
is i can't just have a straight up update right
i i need to something that comes in and says
report my location right now okay maybe i've
checked in at an ice cream stand and then then i
go to like a museum and i you know i want to check
in there and so i i update my location again or
maybe i've got an app that's updating my location
periodically so that my friends know where i'm at
and so um you could call the little update method
here that i created but it updates everything
and we really just want to update one thing
and so and there's a little bit of behavior
to that too because we've got an updated date
for your location we've got a location updated
last time you updated that location and we have
the location and so this feels like something that
needs to be its own api call so i've created that
here it's got a person um you go to the person
slash id location and then longitude and latitude
and so this is a little interface for it uh
let's go ahead and get to the code to do that
so first off i'm going to create a new router
called location router and it's going to have
uh the same url that we just saw in swagger so
the slash person slash id location and then the
longitude and latitude and again we're pulling
those arguments out of the params from that uh
call from express and then we're going to set the
updated date for the location to be uh the current
right now we're going to create a new date and
it's like make the updated date right now then
we fetch the person by that id that we were passed
we set the location to the longitude and latitude
that they were passed in we set the location
updated to that newly created date and then
we save the person and then this will then update
them then we return the id and the date and where
they said they were at so we return the data back
to them and then we need to map this in server.js
so let's go ahead and do that so we'll bring in
that location router and we'll add it to person
and so now we should be able to hit this
url and update a person's location so
who's the last person we got let's uh
let's get all the people here find someone
let's get joan jet let's move her around
and we'll leave we'll leave
her up because i want to
paste that there i want to
copy her latitude and longitude
as well so she's at minus 75 and
positive 40. that's close enough
minus 75 and she's at positive 40. and
so if i execute that that'll update her
location to be exactly that now and so if we
hit our little uh person id and search for her
you can see that her loca longitude and latitude
have now been updated and we will be able to see
this this in redis as well it's fine there she
is so minus 75 comma 40. and if we update it
again then we'll update it again if we look at the
date there we see the unix timestamp is something
a little more it has less zeros at the end of it
which tells us that it's not a nice round date and
we look here it's uh the current date i clearly
recorded this on march the 14th happy pi day um
so cool that updated that's great so we've
got this little thing right it updates their
current location updates their little record
and write a song that json document but
i want to go a little bit further because
one of the things you have when you have like this
tracking app is you don't want just their current
location to be nice to track their history right
so this is where they were and this is where they
were next and this is where they were next like
you know location i checked in here and i checked
into this other place and i checked into this
third place and so how do we do that with redisome
well the answer is that we don't redisome doesn't
do that but redis does redis has a streaming data
type uh where we can show up streaming data if
you're not familiar with streams go check out you
know there's lots of information on streaming data
types out on the internet you can think of them
as a log of hashes uh with a time stamp and uh
the ha the hash containing key value paired data
and um it's um it's like a law it's like a log
file it's a a bunch of events that have occurred
so at this point this event current here's a
bunch of data about it at this point here's
an event data and at this point there's this
event data redis has one of those but redison
can't use it but we can fix that because we can
step underneath retisom and use the underlying
redis client node redis to do this ourselves so
how do we do that well we're going to go back to
our client remember client.js
all those years ago so before
we just had this we got our url we call
client.open pass in the url and export it
now we are importing from redis this is node redis
uh the create client function and instead
of using uh our new client passing it open
uh we use the create client from redis to create
what i'm calling a connection uh but but redis
node redis calls a client as well so
i call a connection to disambiguate
but they're both clients and this is a node
redis instance that we can do anything that
redis can do against and so we create a client
passing in that url we connect to that client
calling connect and then instead of opening on our
client we just tell it to use that connection so
we're just saying we create a new client and
say use the connection instead of calling open
and boom we are now you we now have a redis
connection a node redis connection and we have a
redisome client and they are coexisting peacefully
they're both using this exact same connection
uh this is handy if you want to access commands
on redis that you don't have access to otherwise
from writism it's also handy if you're using
retisome and you wanna use it to connect to
redis in more sophisticated ways than just a
simple url there's lots and lots and lots of
options for how you can connect to redis and you
can access all those with node redis and so this
allows you to do this it's the advanced uh way
of connecting so now we've got a client that uses
noderetis explicitly and we've exported our
redisconnect our redis connection from noderedis
as well as our redison client so now that we've
done that we can start doing redis things so let's
take a look at our location router again and let's
look at the last change we're going to make here
i bring in that connection from from the
client.js i've added one line of code here
i'm calling connection.x add that means stream
ad add something to a stream i'm giving it a key
name for that stream that key name is going to be
the person key so that'd be the person colon ulid
there's a little keyname property
on entity that's created that's very
useful for this purpose and then we just tack
on a location history and so we're saying add to
the a stream in this key and if it doesn't exist
it'll create it add a timestamp of star that means
generate your own stream id the stream id
is made up of a time stamp a unix timestamp
dash and then a serial number in case there's
more than one thing per millisecond star just
means do all that automatically use the server to
do it we don't want to mess with it that's almost
always what you want to do and then we pass
in uh a javascript object with uh name value
pairs in it uh location is made up of longitude
and latitude here right so we can just pass that
in as is and that will update uh the latitude
and longitude for that user every single time
we call this route so let's uh let's do that again
let's let's take joan jett and update her location
to be let's see she's at minus
75 let's put it minus 75.1
and we'll do minus 75.2 and then we'll move
her uh north a little bit she's heading west
now she needs to head head north and
then she's going to head northwest
there we go moving kind of fast there but you know
such as it is so if we uh go out into redis and
look we can see that john jeff's location is now
updated but if we refresh our key list we'll see
there's a stream here and it's got that name
just as we defined it person called eulid on
location history so uh to access the stream
well we could click on it but it just tells us
that this data type isn't supported in a pretty
way yet but we can totally access it from the
cli if we go here so i'm going to copy
this key name just for my convenience
and then we go over to the workbench and we can
just enter redis commands and so we're going to do
x range x range reads a stream
by the key name from a start stream id to an end
stream id or event id um i want all of them so i'm
just going to do minus for the beginning of time
and plus for the end of time and when i run that
we see that there is the most the the older
records are here so the longitude was 75.1 and
40. 75.2 and 40. uh then she started moving
uh um north and then moved northwest so you
can see that entire history of all those uh
movements so now we've got a log pretty cool
so um that's pretty much all i've got um so i
guess this is the part where i say thanks for
hanging out with me and working on this and i hope
it was useful um you've got a decent bit of sample
code sitting on your computer now that you can use
to do uh redisome and a little bit more to really
build a basic api or even a very sophisticated api
uh using redis redisome read a stack and express
so um thanks for hanging out with me doing this
and uh if you have any questions leave them in the
comments or uh or better yet go to discord.gigi
redis which is our redis discord server i'm always
on there and ask questions there and i'll be happy
to answer them and yeah see you next time [Music]